Guide to the Central Washington University Faculty Papers, Michael Jennings 1995-1999
Central Washington University Archives and Special Collections
Central Washington University Associate Vice President of Faculty Affairs, Michael Jennings Collection
1995-1999
Central Washington University, Archives and Special Collections 400 E University Way Ellensburg, WA 98926 (509) 963-1717 http://www.lib.cwu.edu/Archives-Special-Collections archive@cwu.edu
FP-0015
Jennings, Michael L.
3.5 cubic feet 53 video cassettes in 4 video cassette containers and 1 letter sized document case 120-minute VHS video cassettes, transcripts, and newspaper clippings in fair condition, though some video cassettes have very limited audio capabilities.
This collection consists of video cassettes featuring lectures, round table discussions, and debates that focus on Native American history, culture, and governance in the State of Alaska.
Biographical Note
Michael L. Jennings became Associate Vice President of Academic Affairs at Central Washington University in 2005. He received his Bachelor of Arts (1986) and Master of Education (1987) degrees from the University of Alaska, Fairbanks, and his Ph.D. (1995) in Social and Educational Policy Studies from the University of British Columbia. Prior to his arrival at Central, Dr. Jennings served in several positions at the University of Alaska from 1980 to 2005. This included serving as Director of Employee and Labor Relations, Assistant Professor in the School of Education and Native American Studies, and the Director of Alaska Native Studies. Jennings has also authored Native Political Leadership and Higher Education: One University, Two Universes.
This collection consists of video cassettes of experts, politicians, researchers and professors teaching courses, delivering lectures or participating in round table discussions or debates that focus upon Native American history, culture, and governance in the state of Alaska. The majority of video cassettes were recorded at the University of Alaska in Anchorage. The collection was acquired by Michael Jennings, who was the Director of Native American Studies at the University of Alaska from 1997 to 2005. Included in the collection are newspaper clippings related to Native American issues in Alaska from 1997 to 1998, transcripts of audio taped interviews, and biographical information on Dr. Jennings. Sound quality on the vast majority of cassettes is very poor.
Arranged alphabetically by surname of the person presented on the video cassette
Open to the public for research
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Jennings, Michael
University of Alaska Anchorage
Native American history and society; Alaska Natives--Government relations
Native Americans; Alaska
- Clippings and transcripts
  - Alaskan Native American Issues – Newspaper Clippings, 1997 (Box-folder 1-1)
  - Alaskan Native American Issues – Newspaper Clippings, 1997 (Box-folder 1-2)
  - Alaskan Native American Issues – Newspaper Clippings, 1997-1998 (Box-folder 1-3)
  - Alaskan Native American Issues – Newspaper Clippings, 1997-1998 (Box-folder 1-4)
  - Alaskan Native American Issues – Newspaper Clippings, 1998 (Box-folder 1-5)
  - Alaskan Native American Issues – Newspaper Clippings, 1998 (Box-folder 1-6)
  - Biographical information on Michael Jennings (Box-folder 1-7)
  - Anderson, Ralph – Interview transcript (Box-folder 1-8)
  - Demmerit, Dennis – Interview transcript (Box-folder 1-9)
  - Hensley, Willie – Interview transcript (Box-folder 1-10)
  - Holman, George – Interview transcript (Box-folder 1-11)
  - Kito, Sam – Interview transcript (Box-folder 1-12)
  - Knoti, Emil – Interview transcript (Box-folder 1-13)
  - Sackett, John – Interview transcript (Box-folder 1-14)
  - Schafer, John – Interview transcript (Box-folder 1-15)
  - Sturgulewski, Arliss – Interview transcript (Box-folder 1-16)
  - Thompson, Morris – Interview transcript (Box-folder 1-17)
  - Wallis, Timothy – Interview transcript (Box-folder 1-18)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence (Box-folder 1-19)
- Video cassettes
  - Author unknown - Alaska Native Issues – Lecture in class setting (Box-item 2-1)
  - Angapak, Nelson – Alaska Federation of Natives and Subsistence – Lecture in class setting, March 4, 1999 (Box-item 2-2)
  - Ashman, Peter – Tribal Court and Rural Justice in Alaska - Lecture in class setting, November 3, 1998 (Box-item 2-3)
  - Blatchford, Edgar - Impact of the Media on Alaska Natives - Lecture in class setting, September 22, 1998 (Box-item 2-4)
  - Blatchford, Joel – Subsistence Hunting and Fishing in Cook Inlet - Lecture in class setting, January 26, 1999 (Box-item 2-5)
  - Bothelho, Bruce – Tribal Sovereignty and the State of Alaska - Lecture in class setting, October 29, 1998 (Box-item 2-6)
  - Brelsford, Taylor – Historical Overview of Regional Advisory Councils and Federal Takeover of Fisheries - Lecture in class setting, February 4, 1999 (Box-item 2-7)
  - Callaway, Donald – National Park Service and Subsistence - Lecture in class setting, March 9, 1999 (Box-item 2-8)
  - Callaway, Donald - National Park Service and Subsistence(?), Part 2 - Lecture in class setting, March 11, 1999 (Box-item 2-9)
  - Callaway, Donald – Effects of the Exxon Valdez Oil Disaster - Lecture in class setting, April 1, 1999 (Box-item 2-10)
  - Case, David – Federal Indian Property Law and Native Alaskans (1) - Lecture in class setting, October 1, 1998 (Box-item 2-11)
  - Case, David - Federal Indian Property Law and Native Alaskans (2) - Lecture in class setting, October 6, 1998 (Box-item 2-12)
  - Case, David - Federal Indian Property Law and Native Alaskans (3) - Lecture in class setting, October 8, 1998 (Box-item 2-13)
  - Case, David and Mitchell, Donald – Native American Land Claims Debate – Debate before an audience, October 27, 2002 (Box-item 2-14)
  - Case, David and Mitchell, Donald – Native American Land Claims Debate – Debate before an audience (copy 2), October 27, 2002 (Box-item 2-15)
  - Churchill, Ward – Legal Rights and Land Title of the United States Government in Alaska - Roundtable discussion, April 6, 1995 (Box-item 3-16)
  - Churchill, Ward – Indigenous Governance – Lecture before audience, April 7, 1995 (Box-item 3-17)
  - Churchill, Ward – Indigenous Governance – Lecture before audience (copy 2), April 7, 1995 (Box-item 3-18)
  - Churchill, Ward – Indigenous Governance in America: Fact, Fantasy and Prospects for the Future (1) - Lecture before audience (Box-item 3-19)
  - Churchill, Ward – Indigenous Governance in America: Fact, Fantasy and Prospects for the Future (2) - Lecture before audience (Box-item 3-20)
  - Churchill, Ward – Indigenous Governance in America: Fact, Fantasy and Prospects for the Future (1) - Lecture before audience (copy 2) (Box-item 3-21)
  - Churchill, Ward – Indigenous Governance in America: Fact, Fantasy and Prospects for the Future (2) - Lecture before audience (copy 2) (Box-item 3-22)
  - Cole, Charles – Alaska vs. Venetie Tribal Government - Lecture in class setting, September 24, 1998 (Box-item 3-23)
  - Dorough, Dalee Sambo – Tribal Sovereignty and the State of Alaska - Lecture in class setting, September 29, 1998 (Box-item 3-24)
  - Everson, Charles – Question and Answer Session on Academic Courses - Lecture in class setting, December 8, 1998 (Box-item 3-25)
  - Fall, James – Overview of Subsistence in Alaska – Lecture in class setting, February 2, 1999 (Box-item 3-26)
  - Ginnis, Steven – Sovereignty and Tribal Politics - Lecture in class setting, December 1, 1998 (Box-item 3-27)
  - Haycox, Stephen – Historical overview of Native and Non-native Relations – Lecture in class setting, September 10, 1998 (Box-item 3-28)
  - Hildebrand, Ida – Bureau of Indian Affairs and the Federal Subsistence Board -Lecture in class setting, March 2, 1999 (Box-item 3-29)
  - Huhndorf, Roy – Native Claim Settlements in Alaska - Lecture in class setting, December 10, 1998 (Box-item 3-30)
  - Huntington, Henry – Cooperative Co-management of Resources and Subsistence - Lecture in class setting, April 6, 1999 (Box-item 4-31)
  - Hysteer(?), Vicki and Owletuck, George – Tribal Rights and Subsistence – Lecture in class setting, February 18, 1999 (Box-item 4-32)
  - Jennings, Michael – General Discussion on Course Research - Lecture in class setting, November 19, 1998 (Box-item 4-33)
  - La Duke, Winona – Land and Its Significance in Indigenous Perspective – Lecture before audience, April 10, 1997 (Box-item 4-34)
  - Luke, Howard (Alternative School) - Alaska Native Claims Settlement Act Presentation – Panel discussion, December 7, 1995 (Box-item 4-35)
  - Maas, David – State and Native Alaskan Relations - Lecture in class setting, September 1998 (Box-item 4-36)
  - Maas, David – State Policy and Native American Rights Groups - Lecture in class setting, October 13, 1998 (Box-item 4-37)
  - Maas, David – Tribal Self Governance - Lecture in class setting, October 22, 1998 (Box-item 4-38)
  - Maas, David – International Law and Native Americans - Lecture in class setting, November 5, 1998 (Box-item 4-39)
  - Mitchell, Donald – Economic Development and the Alaska Native Claims Settlement Act - Lecture in class setting, November 17, 1998 (Box-item 4-40)
  - Phillips, Gayle – Subsistence Issue and State Government – Teleconference in class setting, October 27, 1998 (Box-item 4-41)
  - Ross, Wayne Anthony – Subsistence and the United States Constitution - Lecture in class setting, February 23, 1999 (Box-item 4-42)
  - Seekins, Ralph and Levengood, Lynn – Boundaries between Native Alaskan Sovereignty and State and Federal Government - Lecture in class setting, October 15, 1998 (Box-item 4-43)
  - Sturgulewski, Arliss – Commission on Rural Governance and Empowerment - Lecture in class setting, November 10, 1998 (Box-item 4-44)
  - Thompson, Kenneth – Proposed Regulations and Subsistence Fishing - Lecture in class setting, March 30, 1999 (Box-item 4-45)
  - Alaska Moving Image Preservation Association – Reunion Under Mount Saint Elias: The Return of Frederica de Laguna to Yakutat, Alaska – Television Program, 1997 (Box-item 5-46)
  - Gwich’in Niintsyaa Steering Committee – Gwich’in Niintsyaa: The 1988 Artic Village Gathering – Television Program (Box-item 5-47)
  - Unknown presenter – Takona Alternate School Project – Promotional Program, 1995 (Box-item 5-48)
  - Multiple presenters – Historic overview: Alaska Native Claims Settlement Act - Class project (Box-item 5-49)
  - Multiple presenters – Indian Country – Panel Discussion (1), March 26, 1997 (Box-item 5-50)
  - Multiple presenters – Indian Country – Panel Discussion (2), March 26, 1997 (Box-item 5-51)
  - Multiple presenters – Native Alaska Sovereignty - Class Presentations (Box-item 5-52)
  - Multiple presenters – Tribal sovereignty and the Future of Alaska Natives – Lecture before audience (Box-item 5-53)